Irving Fineman Papers
Irving Fineman Papers
1919-1976
Fineman, Irving, 1893-1976
40.0 linear ft.
Papers of the Jewish American novelist, author. Correspondence (1919-1976), including a significant number of letters from Julia Peterkin (1926-1943); typescript drafts and revisions of novels, plays, poems, stories; diaries (1922-1949); notebooks; galley proofs; and memorabilia, including calendars, clippings, photographs, and scrapbooks.
148979
Biographical History
Irving Fineman (1893-1976) was a Jewish-American novelist and author. Born in New York City, he earned degrees in civil engineering from both the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Harvard in 1917. Following a term in the U.S. Navy as an engineer officer (1918-1922), he returned to civil engineering, working in the field designing and constructing bridges, subways, etc and also teaching theoretical and applied mechanics at the University of Illinois. In 1928, taken with the idea of writing a novel, he began work on This Pure Young Man, which won a $7500 prize in 1930. By 1932 he was at work on his second novel and had taken a teaching position at Bennington University in Bennington, Vermont. "It was only when I undertook to teach the subject that with my students I made a thoroughgoing and conscious study of literature and the techniques of writing; but by then I had written two books."
In the late 1930s Fineman spent a year or two in Hollywood writing for several studios, but he found that "while motion picture producers were intrigued by the idea of getting something fresh from a serious writer, they almost invariably got cold feet when it came to putting something unusual or controversial before the cameras." By 1950 he had retired from teaching and other occupations to devote his full attention to writing, though he still took time out for projects that interested him. He served as editorial consultant for the RAND Corporation in 1957 and spent a year as scholar in residence at Duke University (1965-1966).
In addition to seven novels and a biography of Henrietta Szold, the founder of Hadassah, Fineman published short stories, poems, and literary criticism in literary and general interest magazines such as Nation, Harper's, Yale Review, New Yorker, New York Times, Saturday Review, and the Los Angeles Times.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Irving Fineman Papers have been arranged into ten series: Clippings, Correspondence, Files, Memorabilia, Miscellaneous printed material, Notes, Writings, Writings – others, Published material, and Writings (unknown)
The collection begins with two boxes of assorted Clippings. Correspondence spans more than sixty years and contains both personal and professional correspondence; correspondents include Anne Walters, Brandeis University, Random House, Frances Frost, and Julia Peterkin.
Files includes medical, legal, and financial material as well as material relating to assorted personal and professional subjects. Memorabilia contains, among other things, calendars and diaries, photographs and scrapbooks, and example of artwork. Miscellaneous printed material consists of books, journals, pamphlets, and magazines, followed by five boxes of miscellaneous Notes.
Writings consists of drafts, galleys, notes, synopses, book covers, and typescripts of novels, plays, poetry, screenplays, and short stories, written by Fineman or by Fineman in collaboration with others. Writings — others and Writings (unknown) is comprised of writings by authors other than Fineman, or writings whose authorship is unknown. Published material contains items by and about Fineman.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is subdivided by type. Files and Memorabilia are arranged alphabetically. Miscellaneous printed material is subdivided by type. The two boxes of Clippings and five boxes of Notes are in no particular order. Fineman's Writings are subdivided by type and then arranged, where appropriate, alphabetically by title; Writings by others and by unknown authors are in no particular order. Published material is subdivided into material by Fineman and material about Fineman.
Related Material
has made a concerted effort over the years to ensure that its manuscript and rare books holdings complement each other. As a result, many of our manuscript collections are supported by books, pamphlets, serials and other items which are cataloged in the Rare Books Collection. Please be sure to search for these related materials.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Fineman, Irving, 1893-1976 -- Archives.; Peterkin, Julia Mood, 1880-1961.; American literature -- 20th century.; American literature -- Jewish authors.; Authors, American.; Jews, American.; Novelists, American.; Calendars (documents); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Drafts (documents); Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Poems.; Scrapbooks.; Screenplays.; Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Clippings
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  - Fragments (Box 3)
  - Postcards, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Fourth Class Mail (Box 3)
  - No Dates, 13 folders (Box 3)
  - With
    - Anne Walters (Box 3)
    - Brandeis University (Box 3)
    - Elick Moll (Box 3)
    - Random House (Box 3)
    - Frances Frost (Box 3A)
  - Personal, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - 1919-1939, 24 folders (Box 4)
  - 1940-1959, 23 folders (Box 5)
  - 1960-1976, 18 folders (Box 6)
  - Julia Peterkin
    - undated (Box 6)
    - 1926-1930, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - 1930-1940, 1943, 12 folders (Box 7)
- Files
  - Household
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Bank, 6 folders (Box 7)
    - Legal (Box 8)
    - Receipts
      - General, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Putney School (Box 8)
    - Tax
      - General (Box 8)
      - 1961-1963 (Box 8)
      - 1970-1975, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - Medical
    - General, 6 folders (Box 9)
    - X-Rays (Box 9)
  - Personal
    - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 9)
    - Bank (Box 10)
    - Bennington College (Box 10)
    - Car (Box 10)
    - Education, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Family, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Hollywood (Box 10)
    - Huntington Hartford Foundation (Box 10)
    - Israel (Box 10)
    - Mutual Housing Association (Box 10)
    - Navy (Box 10)
    - Ramah (Box 10)
    - RAND (Box 10)
    - Reprints (Box 10)
    - Social Security (Box 10)
    - United States Auto Association (Box 10)
    - Veterans Administration (Box 10)
    - Women (Box 10)
- Memorabilia
  - Address Books (Box 10)
  - Art Work (Oversize 2)
  - Awards (Box 10)
  - Business Cards (Box 10)
  - Calendars (Box 10)
  - Calendars, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Diaries (Box 11)
    - 1922 (Box 11)
    - 1930's (Box 11)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 11)
    - 1947 (Box 11)
    - 1948 (Box 11)
    - 1949 (Box 11)
    - After 1949 (Box 11)
  - Family (Box 11)
  - Negatives, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Notebooks, 21 volumes (Box 11)
  - Painting (oil) (Box 12)
  - Passports (Box 12)
  - Photographs, 6 folders (Box 12)
  - Photographs (Oversize 2)
  - Scrapbooks, 3 volumes (Box 12)
  - Scrapbooks, 2 volumes (Oversize 1)
  - Slide (color) (Box 12)
  - Spike (Box 12)
  - Tape Recordings, 4 tapes (Box 12)
  - Textbook (Oversize 1)
  - Triptiks, 2 items (Box 12)
  - Yearbook (Oversize 2)
- Miscellaneous printed material
  - Books, 6 volumes (Box 12)
  - Pamphlets (Box 13)
  - Magazines and Journals (Box 14)
- Notes
  - Miscellaneous notes, 15 folders (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 15 folders (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 15 folders (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 13 folders (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 10 folders (Box 19)
- Writings
  - Notes, 10 folders (Box 20)
  - Photocopied Material, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Ideas, 17 folders (Box 21)
  - Ideas, 16 folders (Box 22)
  - Ideas, 10 folders (Box 23)
  - Novels
    - Doctor Addams
      - Synopsis, 2 folders (Box 23)
      - Bookcover (Box 23)
      - Rough Draft, 4 folders (Box 24)
    - Helen Herself
      - Notes, 4 folders (Box 24)
      - Rough Draft, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Typescripts, 7 folders (Box 24)
    - Here Ye Sons
      - Miscellaneous (Box 25)
      - Bookcover (Box 25)
      - Galley (Box 25)
      - Typescript, 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Jacob
      - Notes, 4 folders (Box 25)
      - Typescripts, 4 folders (Box 25)
    - Lovers Must Learn
      - Rough Draft (Box 25)
      - Bookcover (Box 25)
      - Typescripts, 5 folders (Box 26)
    - Mystery on Maple Hill
      - Typescripts, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Pieta
      - Rough Drafts, 13 folders (Box 26)
      - Rough Drafts, 17 folders (Box 27)
      - Rough Drafts, 3 folders (Box 28)
      - Typescripts, 9 folders (Box 28)
      - Typescripts, 2 folders (Box 29)
      - Postscript, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Ruth
      - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 29)
      - Notes, 5 folders (Box 29)
      - Rough Drafts, 2 folders (Box 29)
      - Rough Drafts, 2 folders (Box 30)
      - Typescripts, 4 folders (Box 30)
      - Motion picture adaptation (Box 30)
      - Galley (Box 30)
      - Book (Box 30)
    - This Pure Young Man
      - Bookcover (Box 30)
      - Correspondence (Box 30)
      - Clippings (Box 30)
      - Legal (Box 30)
      - Notes, 3 folders (Box 30)
      - Typescripts (Box 30)
      - Typescripts, 4 volumes (Box 31)
    - Woman of Valor
      - Bookcover (Box 31)
      - Research Material, 2 folders (Box 31)
      - Notes, 5 folders (Box 31)
      - Rough Draft, 2 folders (Box 32)
      - Typescripts, 3 folders (Box 32)
      - Galleys, 2 folders (Box 32)
      - Book (Box 32)
  - Plays
    - A Boy A Girl And A Dog, 3 folders (Box 32)
    - Akiba, 2 folders (Box 32)
    - The Fig Tree Madonna, 12 folders (Box 33)
    - Here Comes Miss Jordan (Box 33)
    - If This Be Known (Box 33)
    - Little Red Riding Hood (Box 33)
    - The Long Road (Box 33)
    - Mr. Jordan Calling (Box 33)
    - The Lives of Patricia (Box 33)
    - Oedipus (Box 33)
    - For Mortals (Box 33)
    - Husbands Ltd. (Box 33)
    - The Widow of Ephesus (Box 33)
  - Poems, 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Poems, 9 folders (Box 34)
  - Screenplays, A-Z, 8 folders (Box 34)
  - Short Stories
    - Misc., 5 folders (Box 35)
    - A-K, 14 folders (Box 35)
    - L-Z, 15 folders (Box 36)
  - With Others
    - w/ Jerry Horwin, 2 folders (Box 37)
    - w/ Carl A. Halter (Box 37)
    - w/ Herbert Kline, 3 folders (Box 37)
- Writings – others
  - Miscellaneous, 12 folders (Box 37)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 38)
- Published material
  - By Fineman, 3 folders (Box 38)
  - About Fineman (Box 38)
- Writings (unknown)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 38)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 39)